{
  "reference_number": "1074",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "The Government needs to set progressive targets 2020, 2030, 2040, 2050 in legislation now with the goal to be reaching net zero\n emissions by 2050 at the latest. The Climate Change Commission should monitor, advise but also have the power to veto\n government decisions if they interfere with meeting the emissions targets"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "If accepting emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) means that current intensive land and water usage\n\n practices continue (intensive dairy farming in particular) as usual, this is unethical and shortsighted. If we meet the emissions targets\n at the cost of our water quality and ecosystem balance, then we are just creating more problems to solve in a future where we will be\n facing greater resource restrictions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "If any emissions budget changes are allowed, they may only be to further reduce the third budget in the sequence. There is no\n\n scope to become more lenient as time goes on. The option I have selected does not specify that the Govt should have this option;\n and they should not have absolute power over it. The independent Climate Change Commission should be the body to determine\n the emissions budget and the Govt should be expected to act in response to what the Commission decides"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "We will potentially face a greater number of natural disasters in the future as the climate changes, resulting from the damage already\n\ndone. This situation is not going to improve if we continue to review and adjust the targets. In the wake of a serious disaster,\nresource allocation may mean a larger portion of the emissions budget is spent rapidly, which leaves less of the budget for the\nsubsequent period. That's all we can afford. These 'exceptional circumstance' events will require a shift away from business-as-usual\n\nfollowing them if there is to be any significant change. If we have the option to regress to greater emission rates, we are closing our\nwindow of opportunity to stabilise the climate. The feedback effects associated with (temperature extremes, storms, droughts) will\n\nnot reduce in severity and what are now exceptional circumstances may tend to be the norm"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Business competitiveness doesn't really have a place in this area; we need people working together not in competition. I don't see\nbusiness competitiveness expertise necessary in the panel, or even desirable,"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The most vulnerable people (living in low lying, low socio-economic zones) need to be considered. If setting a plan means their food\n\nor job security is compromised, there needs to be some sort of support for them in the transition too. A fair and just transition must\nbe fair and just for all. Public transport options to replace vehicles and infrastructure to a low carbon system (changing the perception\n\nof vehicle ownership, providing bike or e-bike share schemes, funding electric bus, van and car conversions - which promote skilled,\nlocal industry and are aligned with a low emissions economy) The massive environmental degradation and emissions caused by the\nagricultural sector cannot be ignored. Agricultural emissions have to be included in the budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Commission cannot just be an observer or placed on the periphery of the Govt's agenda, but needs to have the power to make\n\nthe targets for the Govt to see met. The Commission should reflect what is best for the climate and as an independent entity from\nthe Government, should have the power to veto the Government when decisions are made contrary to meeting emissions targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The NZ ETS needs an overhaul. If the Commission is hoping to make a meaningful contribution to the future of Aotearoa, it needs to\n\nhave the power to set the targets / available units for the Govt to follow. Agricultural emissions need to be considered in the ETS for it\nto be more meaningful and representative. If the Commission is independent of the Govt and has a role focussed on reducing the\nseverity of climate change, then it will have the power to bypass the lobbyists pushing for exemptions in the agricultural sector"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I agree with the following proposed essential expertise and half of the desirable expertise • climate change policy (including\n\nemissions trading) • resource economics and impacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) • te Tiriti o Waitangi,\nte reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori interests • climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori • experience with\n\naddressing adaptation challenges like planning, insurance and local government • risk management • engineering and/or\ninfrastructure • community engagement and communications. • knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology\n\ndevelopment system."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The climate is already different than from when I was growing up. We need education and a framework to help make communities and\nthe economy to be more resilient and adaptable to the changes we will be facing"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If the UK has had better results from mandatory reporting, we may also have better uptake from implements mandatory adaptation\n\nreporting."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We are all in this together. The highly competitive business model needs re-structuring to have a more collaborative element. If there\nare risks that some organisations are aware of, this should be available and accessible to all that it affects."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Please implement a framework that makes meaningful positive differences to the environment and the people of Aotearoa.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
